Nathan Lewis Miller Papers
Nathan Lewis Miller Papers
1902-1958
Miller, Nathan L., 1868-1953.
15 linear ft.
Papers of the New York Governor (1921 to 1922), attorney, General Counsel of U.S. Steel Corporation. Collection contains correspondence, both incoming and outgoing (1902-1958); legal briefs; writings (1922-1953); and memorabilia including family photographs and scrapbooks of political cartoons and clippings (1921-1922). Correspondents include Roger Blough, Calvin Coolidge, Richard Coughlin, Charles Crandall, Frederick Crane, Thomas E. Dewey, John Foster Dulles, Dwight D. Eisenhower, Benjamin Fairless, James A. Farley, Livingstone Farrand, James W. Fawcett, Haley Fiske, Edgar Allen Forbes, George A. Glynn, Will H. Hays, Christian Herter, Richmond Hobson, Herbert Hoover, Charles Evans Hughes, Cordell Hull, Alfred Landon, Herbert Lehman, Irving Lehman, Clayton Lusk, Albert Mann, J.P. Morgan, Irving Olds, Joseph Proskauer, Franklin D. Roosevelt, Theodore Roosevelt, Flem Sampson, Alfred E. Smith, Edward R. Stettinius, Henry Stoddard, William H. Taft, Myron Taylor, Arthur Vandenberg, Paul Vernon, Enders Voorhees, Carl Vrooman, William Wadhams, Wilbur Wakeman, John Weeks, Everett Wheeler, Horace White, and Wendell Willkie.
149165
Biographical History
Nathan Lewis Miller (1868-1953) was an American conservative politician and attorney. He was New York State Comptroller from 1901 to 1903 and sat on the New York State Supreme Court from 1903-1915. He served as Governor of New York (1921-1922) and as General Counsel of U.S. Steel Corporation (1925- ).
Scope and Contents of the Collection
The Nathan Lewis Miller Papers comprise correspondence, legal briefs, memorabilia, and writings of the lawyer and New York State Governor (1921-1922). Spanning the years 1902 to 1958, the collection reflects Miller's public life as New York State Comptroller, State Supreme Court Justice, and Governor as well as his private law practice and his service as General Counsel for United States Steel Corporation.
The correspondence (Box 1) is arranged chronologically with a selected index of correspondents at the end of the inventory, and is in both volume and substance most heavily concentrated in the 1920s. An activist in both state and national Republican Party politics, Miller included among his correspondents Calvin Coolidge, Thomas Dewey, John Foster Dulles, Dwight D. Eisenhower, Herbert Hoover, Charles Evans Hughes, Cordell Hull, Alfred M. Landon, Herbert Lehman, Franklin Roosevelt, William Howard Taft, Robert F. Wagner and Wendell Willkie. In addition to the political correspondence are a number of letters involving Miller's trusteeship of Cornell University and several others which concern financial matters.
Boxes 2-4 of the collection contain printed legal briefs for four of Miller's cases, memorabilia, including photographs and a scrapbook of obituaries, and writings. The writings include two drafts and the printed version of Miller's theory about the authorship of Shakespeare's plays, a printed copy of his autobiographical Recollections (1953), and three volumes of speeches, mostly in mimeographed form, from the 1922 gubernatorial campaign.
In addition, there are 6 oversized packages of memorabilia, including two commissions, two photograph albums, one photograph, and five scrapbooks, dated 1921-1922. One of the scrapbooks contains mainly newspaper cartoons and photographs of Miller, while the others are mostly newspaper clippings.
Arrangement of the Collection
Correspondence is arranged chronologically. Other material is arranged alphabetically by type or title.
Subject and Genre Headings
New York State; Politics, government and public administration; Blough, Roger M. (Roger Miles), 1904-1985.; Coolidge, Calvin, 1872-1933.; Coughlin, Richard.; Crandall, Charles H. (Charles Henry), 1858-1923.; Crane, Frederick E. (Frederick Evan), 1869-1947.; Dewey, Thomas E. (Thomas Edmund), 1902-1971.; Dulles, John Foster, 1888-1959.; Eisenhower, Dwight D. (Dwight David), 1890-1969.; Fairless, Benjamin F. (Benjamin Franklin), 1890-; Farley, James A. (James Aloysius), 1888-1976.; Farrand, Livingston, 1867-1939.; Fawcett, James Waldo, 1893-1968.; Fiske, Haley, 1852-1929.; Forbes, Edgar Allen, 1872-; Glynn, George A.; Hays, Will H. (Will Harrison), 1879-1954.; Herter, Christian Archibald, 1895-1966.; Hobson, Richmond Pearson, 1870-1937.; Hoover, Herbert, 1874-1964.; Hughes, Charles Evans, 1862-1948.; Hull, Cordell, 1871-1955.; Lamont, Thomas W. (Thomas William), 1870-1948.; Landon, Alfred M. (Alfred Mossman), 1887-1987.; Lehman, Herbert H. (Herbert Henry), 1878-1963.; Lehman, Irving, 1876-1945.; Lusk, Clayton R. (Clayton Riley), b. 1872.; Mann, Albert Russell, 1880-1947.; Miller, Nathan L., 1868-1953.; Morgan, J. P. (John Pierpont), 1867-1943.; Olds, Irving Sands, 1887-; Proskauer, Joseph M. (Joseph Meyer), 1877-1971.; Roosevelt, Franklin D. (Franklin Delano), 1882-1945.; Roosevelt, Theodore, 1887-1944.; Sampson, Flem D.; Smith, Alfred Emanuel, 1873-1944.; Stettinius, Edward R., Jr. (Edward Reilly), 1900-1949.; Stoddard, Henry L. (Henry Luther), 1861-1947.; Taft, William H. (William Howard), 1857-1930.; Taylor, Myron Charles, 1874-1959.; Vandenberg, Arthur H. (Arthur Hendrick), 1884-1951.; Vernon, Paul E. (Paul Egbert), b. 1869.; Voorhees, Enders M. (Enders McClumpha), b. 1891.; Vrooman, Carl Schurz, 1872-1966.; Wadhams, William H. (William Henderson), 1873-1952.; Wakeman, Wilbur F.; Weeks, John W. (John Wingate), 1860-1926.; Wheeler, Everett Pepperrell, 1840-1925.; White, Horace, 1834-1916.; Willkie, Wendell L. (Wendell Lewis), 1892-1944.; Republican Party (N.Y.); Republican Party (U.S.: 1854- ); United States Steel Corporation.; Governors -- New York (State); New York (State) -- Politics and government, 1865-1950.; Clippings (information artifacts); Correspondence.; Photographs.; Scrapbooks.; Attorneys.; Governors.
Access Restrictions
The majority of our archival and manuscript collections are housed offsite and require advanced notice for retrieval. Researchers are encouraged to contact us in advance concerning the collection material they wish to access for their research.
Acquisition Information
Gift of the Miller Family and U.S. Steel Corp., 1965 and 1969.
Inventory
- Correspondence
  - General, 1902-1958; 17 folders (Box 1)
  - General, undated (Box 1)
- Legal briefs
  - United States of America v. Columbia Steel Company [et al.], 2 folders (Box 2)
  - United States of America vs. Elgin, Joliet and Eastern Railway Company (Box 2)
  - United States Steel Corporation [et al.] v. Federal Trade Commission (Box 2)
  - The Youngstown Sheet and Tube Company [et al.] v. Charles Sawyer (Box 2)
- Memorabilia
  - Awards (Box 2)
  - Certificate of appointment as State Comptroller, 1901 (Oversize 14)
  - Certificate of appointment as Associate Justice of the Appellate Division of the Supreme Court for the Second Judicial Department, 1904 (Oversize 14)
  - Photograph albums
    - New York State canal system inspection trip, Aug. 15-20, 1921 (Oversize 13)
    - [untitled], New York State gubernatorial duties, portraits, group photos, etc. (Oversize 13)
  - Photographs (Box 2)
  - Portrait photograph of Miller (Oversize 14)
  - Scrapbooks, pages and clippings are in extremely fragile and brittle condition; scrapbooks are numbered for ease of reference, but the material is not always in chronological order
    - [Obituaries] (Box 2)
    - [Clippings, volume 1], 1921-1922; articles on political and governmental topics (Oversize 1)
    - [Clippings, volume 1 cont.], 1921-1922; articles on political and governmental topics (Oversize 2)
    - [Clippings, volume 1 cont.], 1921-1922; articles on political and governmental topics (Oversize 3)
    - [Clippings, volume 1 cont.], 1921-1922; articles on political and governmental topics (Oversize 4)
    - [Clippings, volume 1 cont.], 1921-1922; articles on political and governmental topics (Oversize 5)
    - [Clippings, volume 2], 1921-1922; articles on political and governmental topics (Oversize 6)
    - [Clippings, volume 3], 1921-1922; articles on political and governmental topics (Oversize 7)
    - [Clippings, volume 3 cont.], 1921-1922; articles on political and governmental topics (Oversize 8)
    - [Clippings, volume 3 cont.], 1921-1922; articles on political and governmental topics (Oversize 9)
    - [Clippings, volume 3 cont.], 1921-1922; articles on political and governmental topics (Oversize 10)
    - [Clippings, volume 4], 1921-1922; articles on political and governmental topics (Oversize 11)
    - [Clippings, volume 4 cont.], 1921-1922; articles on political and governmental topics (Oversize 12)
    - [Clippings, volume 5], 1921-1922; cartoons, newspaper photographs, miscellaneous (Oversize 14)
- Writings
  - "A Lawyer's Evaluation of the Evidence Relating to the Authorship of the Shakespearean Literature"
    - Draft A (Box 2)
    - Draft B (Box 2)
    - Correspondence, 1950-1952; 2 folders (Box 2)
  - Recollections, 1953 (Box 2)
  - Speeches for gubernatorial campaign, 1922; 2 volumes (Box 3)
  - Speeches for gubernatorial campaign, 1922; 1 volume (Box 4)
Selected Index to Correspondence
Anderson, William H.20 Oct. 1922
Barrett, Henry R.17 Sept. 1925 22 Sept. 1925
Bartlett, Willard4 May 1922
Blough, Roger Miles23 Dec. 1943 25 Dec. 1943
Breed, William Constable17 Sept. 1925 22 Sept. 1925
Brown, Franklin R.11 June 1954
Chamberlain, Arthur1 Oct. 1951 22 Jan. 1952
Clark, John Proctor16 Sept. 1920 19 Oct. 1921 15 July 1922 26 July 1922
Collin, Frederick1 Oct. 1925
Coolidge, Calvin7 Dec. 1923 8 Dec. 1923 13 June 1924 16 June 1924 5 Nov. 1924 7 Nov. 1924
Coughlin, Richard20 Aug. 1921
Crandall, Charles Henry28 Mar. 1921 2 Apr. 1921
Crane, Frederick E.29 Mar. 1921 1 Apr. 1921
Cromwell, Seymour L.1 Nov. 1922 8 Nov. 1922
Crouse, H. B.12 Apr. 1921 13 Apr. 1921
Cullinan, Patrick W.17 Sept. 1925 22 Sept. 1925
Davis, Rowland L.28 Oct. 1929 29 Oct. 1929
Davison, George W.Sept. 1925 22 Sept. 1925
Delatour, Hunter L.3 Jan. 1955
Dewey, Thomas Edmund11 Dec. 1939 25 Oct. 1944 26 Oct. 1944 6 Nov. 1947 7 Nov. 1947 28 May 1948 25 June 1948 1 July 1948
Dulles, John Foster15 Nov. 1949 5 Dec. 1949
Eisenhower, Dwight David18 Oct. 1949 31 Oct. 1949
Fairless, Benjamin F.7 Nov. 1944 27 Dec. 1944 29 Dec. 1944
Farley, James Aloysius5 Feb. 1947
Farrand, Livingston17 Oct. 1922
Fawcett, James Waldo29 Jan. 1921
Finley, John Huston20 Aug. 1921 25 Aug. 1921
Fiske, Haley17 Sept. 1925 22 Sept. 1925
Forbes, Edgar Allen19 Apr. 1921 22 Apr. 1921
Glynn, George A.12 Jan. 1922 13 Jan. 1922
Hatch, Edward Wingate15 Apr. 1915 21 Apr. 1915 29 Apr. 1915 3 June 1915
Hay, Mary Garrett12 Jan. 1921 13 Jan. 1921 16 Mar. 1921
Hays, Will HarrisonSept. 1925 22 Sept. 1925
Heath, Julian (Mrs.)see National Housewives League, Inc.
Herter, Christian19 Dec. 1922
Hiscock, Frank H.17 Sept. 1925 22 Sept. 1925 17 Apr. 1946
Hobson, Richmond Pearson16 Nov. 1921
Hogg, William B.4 Feb. 1921 14 Feb. 1921
Hoover, Herbert26 Dec. 1922 26 Oct. 1927 13 Jan. 1928 16 Jan. 1928 7 Nov. 1938 12 Nov. 1938 29 Dec. 1950 6 May 1958
Hughes, Charles Evans16 Apr. 1924 19 Apr. 1924 21 Apr. 1924 22 Apr. 1924 5 Nov. 1924 7 Nov. 1924 4 Feb. 1930 6 Feb. 1930
Hull, Cordellundated
Knapp, Kemper K.16 Sept. 1925 22 Sept. 1925
Kresel, Isidor Jacob17 Sept. 1925 22 Sept. 1925
Lamont, Thomas William18 Mar. 1943 (2 items)
Landon, Alfred Mossman10 Mar. 1936 8 May 1936 12 May 1936 26 May 1936
Lehman, Herbert Henry30 Jan. 1934 12 Feb. 1934 2 Jan. 1936
Lehman, Irving 22 Jan. 1935 23 Jan. 1935
Lusk, Clayton Riley15 June 1921 5 June 1941
McKee, Joseph V.26 Oct. 1932 28 Oct. 1932
McLaughlin, Chester Bentine17 Sept. 1925 22 Sept. 1925
Mann, Albert Russell28 Oct. 1921
Meyer, Eugene19 Sept. 1925 22 Sept. 1925
Morgan, John Pierpont12 Sept. 1927
Murray, John Gregory17 Dec. 1938 27 Dec. 1938
National Housewives League, Inc.10 Jan. 1921 12 Jan. 1921 16 Mar. 1921
Nixon, S. F.21 Jan. 1902
Olcott, Jacob Van Vechten29 Dec. 1921
Olds, Irving Sands24 Dec. 1940 30 Dec. 1940 23 Dec. 1942 28 Dec. 1942 23 Dec. 1943 27 Dec. 1943 1 Nov. 1944
Proskauer, Joseph Meyer6 Apr. 1947 5 Dec. 1947
Prosser, Seward19 Oct. 1925 20 Oct. 1925
Roosevelt, Franklin Delano7 July 1938 (enclosure to Stettinius letter) 27 May 1941 3 June 1941
Roosevelt, Theodore8 Oct. 1923 16 Oct. 1923
Sampson, Flem D.11 Apr. 1929 15 Apr. 1929
Schmuck, Peter23 June 1941 24 June 1941 22 Dec. 1941 (2 items)
Smith, Alfred Emanuel25 Feb. 1928 27 Feb. 1928 29 Dec. 1943 4 Jan. 1944
Stettinius, Edward Reilly8 July 1938
Stewart, John Appleton27 Sept. 1921
Stoddard, Henry Luther3 Aug. 1922 2 Nov. 1925 4 Nov. 1925
Taft, William Howard19 May 1922 22 May 1922
Taylor, Myron Charles12 Jan. 1938 14 Jan. 1938 7 Apr. 1938 11 Apr. 1938 12 Apr. 1938 23 Dec. 1942 24 Dec. 1942 undated
Trainor, Val10 Oct. 1922 13 Oct. 1922 16 Oct. 1922 19 Oct. 1922 26 Oct. 1922
Vandenberg, Arthur Hendrick30 Dec. 1920 5 Jan. 1921
Vanderbilt, Cornelius23 Sept. 1922
Vanderlip, Narcissa Cox5 July 1921 (2 items) 8 July 1921
Vernon, Paul Egbert9 Dec. 1920
Voorhees, Enders McClumpha23 Dec. 1938 27 Dec. 1938 21 Dec. 1942 23 Dec. 1942 20 Dec. 1943 23 Dec. 1943 19 Dec. 1944
Vrooman, Carl Schurz14 May 1921 18 May 1921
Vrooman, John Wright12 Nov. 1921 14 Nov. 1921
Wadhams, William Henderson11 Jan. 1922
Wagner, Robert F.19 Apr. 1932 12 July 1932
Wakeman, Wilbur F.5 Sept. 1922 12 Sept. 1922
Ward, Hamilton27 Apr. 1922 3 May 1922
Wardwell, Florence22 July 1921 2 Aug. 1921 9 Jan. 1922 10 Jan. 1922 12 Jan. 1922 13 Jan. 1922 26 Jan. 1922 31 Jan. 1922
Weeks, John Wingate9 Mar. 1921 14 Mar. 1921
Wendell, Ten Eyck14 Oct. 1922 18 Oct. 1922
Wheeler, Everett Pepperrell19 Oct. 1920
White, Horace5 Jan. 1922 10 Jan. 1922 16 Sept. 1925 22 Sept. 1925
Whitman, Russell R.23 Sept. 1922 25 Sept. 1922
Willcox, Julius Abner4 Feb. 1921 16 Feb. 1921
Willkie, Wendell Lewis12 July 1940 13 July 1940 24 July 1940 26 July 1940 22 Sept. 1941 Sept. 1941 (2 items)